Guide to the Cynthia Earl Kerman Papers Relating to The Lives of Jean Toomer
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Cynthia Earl Kerman Papers Relating to The Lives of Jean Toomer
1959-1982
JWJ MSS 116
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.73
(7 boxes)
Research files, including notes, manuscripts, printed material, photographs, and audio tapes compiled by Cynthia Earl Kerman in the process of writing The Lives of Jean Toomer.
Kerman, Cynthia Earl
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Cynthia Earl Kerman (1923-2012)
Cynthia Earl Kerman, biographer of Jean Toomer.
Scope and Contents
Research files, including notes, manuscripts, printed material, photographs, and audio tapes compiled by Cynthia Earl Kerman in the process of writing The Lives of Jean Toomer.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cynthia Earl Kerman, 2000.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: July 2000 Acquisition and January 2013 Acquisition.
Biographers -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Modernism (Literature); Harlem Renaissance; American literature -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiocassettes -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Biographers -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Kerman, Cynthia Earl ( Lives of Jean Toomer); Kerman, Cynthia Earl; Toomer, Jean, 1894-1967; Toomer, Marjorie, 1895-1984
- July 2000 Acquisition, 7
  Arrangement
  Organized into eight series: I. Biographical Research Files, 1923-1984. II. Notes and Copies of Writings by Toomer, 1949-1982. III. People Connected With Toomer, 1978-1987. IV. Interviews (Transcriptions), 1970-1983. V. Interviews (Audiocassettes), 1975-1983. VI. Chronological Notes, 1983-1995. VII. Unsorted Research Files, 1982-1983. VIII. Printed Material, 1966-1982.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 6 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Biographical Research Files, 1923-1984; Series I
    - Buckingham meeting, 1923, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal appreciations, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Personality quirks, 1980-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Toomer photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Toomer and race, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Writings about Toomer, 1969-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Criticisms of Toomer, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Copies of Writings by Toomer, 1949-1982; Series II
    - Alphabetical list with dates and Kerman's notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bibliography and notes on Toomer, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Toomer's autobiography
      - Notes on relationship of segments, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Earth-Being introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Books II and III, Earth-Being (from MCT collection), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - From Exile Into Being, version I, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - From Exile Into Being, version II, part 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - From Exile Into Being, version II, part 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Blue Meridian, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - First trip to Fontainebleau (1955-1956), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Flavor of Man, 1949, 1974, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Friends Intelligencer items (1943-1950), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Gallonwerps (1927-1928), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - An interpretation of Friends worship, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Minor writing before 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lecturing and minor writing after 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Negro Emergent (1925), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Portage potential, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Psychologic series (1937), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Race problems and modern society (1928-1929), undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Notes on religion, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Remember and return and first statements, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Roads, people and principles, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Transatlantic, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Values and fictions, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - People Connected With Toomer, 1978-1987; Series III
    - Morely Ayearst, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Douglas Campbell, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Chicago group, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hart Crane, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Aaron Douglas and Katherine Mansfield, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Walter Driscoll, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Waldo Frank, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Friends of Marjorie Content Toomer and Jean Toomer, 1981-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Zona Gale, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Gurdjieff and Toomer, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Margery Latimer, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Meridel le Sueur, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Mabel Dodge Luhan, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Margo Latimer, 1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Margaret Naumburg, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - A. R. Orage, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Emily Otis, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - P. B. S. Pinchback, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Stieglitz and O'Keeffe, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Edith and Paul Taylor, 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Nathan and Nina Toomer, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Interviews (Transcriptions), 1970-1983; Series IV
    - Lewis Benson, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Frank and Lee Bjornsgaard, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Lin Davenport, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Elizabeth and Georges Duval, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Sally Fell, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Marian Fuson, 1975, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Nancy Geiger, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Katherine Green, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Charles Ingerman, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Mavis McIntosh, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Larry and Ruth Miller, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Byron and Betty Morehouse, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Gorham Munson, 1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Elizabeth Delza Munson, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Edith Passmore, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Dorothy Paxson, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Miryam Ralph (1953-1967), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Susan Sandberg, 1975, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Douglas and Dorothy Steere, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Marjorie Content Toomer: 6 interviews, 1974-1983; 6 (Box 4, Folder 73-78)
    - Marjorie Content Toomer, Shockley interview, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Marjorie Content Toomer, references by others, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Louise and William Welch, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Interviews (Audiocassettes), 1975-1983; Series V
    Box 6 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Marjorie Toomer / Elise Boulding / Larry Miller, 1974 November 12 - 1975 January 23; 1; 01:41:15; There is static and high background noise on the tape. There is a speed issue toward the end of the recording. The program ends abruptly. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399338)
    - Louise and William Welch (Tape III) / Elizabeth Delza Munson (Tape I), 1982 June 25; 1; 01:32:15; There is static and high background noise on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399361)
    - Marjorie Toomer / Dorothy Paxson / Douglas and Dorothy Steere, 1975 January 24; 1; 01:46:31; There is static and warbling during the program. There is high background noise on the tape. The program is distorted at times. There are tape speed issues at the beginning and end of the recording. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399346)
    - Louise and William Welch (Tape II), 1982 June 25; 1; 01:30:59; There is static and high background noise on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399353)
    - Louise and William Welch (Tape I), 1982 June 25; 1; 02:05:00; There is static and high background noise on the tape. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399312)
    - Elizabeth Delza Munson (Tape II), 1982 June 25; 1; 00:55:41; Program begins abruptly. Left channel drops and fades back at the beginning of the audio recording. Static is on the tape. Program is distorted at times and there is a high amount of hiss on the tape. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399304)
    - Margo Toomer Latimer, undated; 1; 01:53:02; There is high frequency background noise on the tape. The audio begins to degrade at about 01:20:00 and becomes unintelligible. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399320)
    - Sue Sandberg and MCT, 1983 March 20; 1; 01:01:09; Program begins and ends abruptly. There is static and a high amount of hiss on the tape. (Box 6, Item barcode 39002091399296)
  - Chronological Notes, 1983-1995; Series VI
    - Notes before 1921, 1983-1995 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Notes on 1922-1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Notes on Toomer's interpretation of 1926 experience, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Notes on 1929-1934, 1983, 1992, undated; 3 (Box 4, Folder 85-87)
    - Marjorie Content Toomer, contemporary notes, 1936-37, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Notes on India trip, 1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Notes on 1940-1944, undated; 4 (Box 4, Folder 90-93)
    - Notes on 1945-1954, undated; 7 (Box 5, Folder 94-100)
    - Notes on Toomer's 1955 journal, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Notes on 1955-1967, undated; 2 (Box 5, Folder 102-103)
  - Unsorted Research Files, 1982-1983; Series VII
    - Assorted notes, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Comments, Elizabeth Delza Munson, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Dates for Toomer, undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Gurdjieff and Ouspensky references, undated; 2 (Box 5, Folder 107-108)
    - Sources, undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Krasny dissertation, undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Mintz thesis, undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Printed Material, 1966-1982; Series VIII
    - Anderson, Margaret: The Unknowable Gurdjieff, 1973 (Box A)
    - Gurdjieff: Views from the Real World, 1975 (Box A)
    - Haskins, James: Pinckney Benton Stewart, 1973 (Box A)
    - Hulme, Kathryn: Undiscovered Country. In Search of Gurdjieff, 1966 (Box A)
    - A Journal of Our Time, 1982 November 3 (Box A)
    - Nicoll, Maurice: Psychological Commentaries on the Teachings of Gurdjieff and Ouspensky, 1957 (Box A)
- January 2013 Acquisition, 1
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "The Jean Toomer Story" photograph album, undated (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Correspondence with Marjorie Toomer, 1979-1983 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Transcription of interviews with Marjorie Toomer, 1975-1983 (Box 7, Folder 114)